howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show listeners have asked us to
provide pointers some of the resources
we talked about on the show we now have
links to books and articles referenced
in recent podcasts that are available on
our website
we also offer full transcripts go to Jim
rut show.com that's Jim ruts show com
this is a special extra episode that
will not be up to our usual impeccable
audio standards there will be quite a
bit shorter and it'll be on a single
topic today's guest is John rabe an
amazing thinker and writer who his main
platform is called global gorilla
John what's your URL well you can find
me on patreon it's the Global gorillas
report or just look John Robb patreon
that's my euro and I've been a longtime
supporter of John Rob's work through
patreon and it's worthy work and I'd
encourage you to support him as well
thanks yeah John's got a very
interesting background he's a graduate
of the Air Force Academy served seven
years in the Air Force for entering the
private sector as it masters from Yale
worked in a sort of IT research done all
kinds interesting things is entrepreneur
and was one of the guys that helped
invent blogging you know since 2004 he's
been doing global guerrillas which has
been about the most interesting deep and
thoughtful analysis on current events
world situation tactics strategy and
perspectives about the future so and I
started to put this idea in together for
a series of short extras about the
coronavirus I thought who better to have
on to kick it off than John rabe so John
give us your perspective where are we at
now what's important what are
distractions what's the signal what's
the noise okay well um there's some good
news and there's some bad news I'll give
you some of the good news first we were
able to recover somewhat from some of
the planning area errors that
were slowing our response to the
pandemic I mean that pandemics had been
planned for planned against for decades
I mean stretching back in the 70s the
problem is our pandemic planning assumed
the world of 1980s or 90s you know much
slower world no one as complex and as
fast-moving is as this one so that
caused three major problems one was that
there was a policy of only shutting off
air traffic to specific countries only
after you know deliberation they shut
off that air traffic rather than
everything at once in a very connected
world that you know shutting off air
traffic to one country just just doesn't
do it or you know quarantine eating all
the passengers coming in just from one
country just doesn't do it them you know
that kind of blockage sure damage is
easily routed around in this kind of
system we're still not fully shut down
on air travel side but or better than we
were the second one was that the we
would have time to ramp up testing and
so the way the FDA handled the testing
situation is that they were focusing on
quality and they gave the CDC a monopoly
on testing production which seemed
reasonable for a slow-moving
pandemic or you know relatively so and
when the CDC screwed up you know single
point of failure at the end of February
you know the wheels came off the bus it
and the FDA responded by saying okay
we'll have a streamlined procedure for
from you know independent labs or public
health labs to apply for starting
testing and everyone pushed back you
know a streamlined procedure what the
hell are you talking about this is this
should be like all hands assholes and
elbows you let's go and they ended up
saying okay well anyone who's already
authorized for complex testing get going
and so they zoomed up the testing and
the testing has been really a really
strong response on the on the part of
labs in the states I mean on March 1st
we produced I think about 266 tests and
the ramp has been meteoric since then we
are up to
Oh has of yesterday sixty-five thousand
deaths a day and that it's much higher
than you know other countries out there
you know Britain is trying to do four
thousand a day I think they're under
that trying to ramp Germany does about
twelve thousand least delay the summers
I saw and they're trying to ramp South
Korea was ten to sixteen for quite a
long time they I think they pushed it up
to twenty just recently and so we're not
up to their level in terms of per
million person you know million
population but we're on the right
trajectory were just we're just zooming
it or hitting out of the park and the
third thing was the medical
manufacturing we let almost everything
that manufactured in the medical field
go off to China and other places and
then we're caught flat-footed and the
assumption that we'd have months to ramp
up our production and that you know
relatively small amounts of strategic
supplies or strategic stockpiles would
be enough to get us through we're all
wrong I mean it is a you know
come-as-you-are situation I mean it
happened so fast they what you have on
hand is what gets you through and our
thinking and our planning assumptions
we're all wrong and there wasn't really
anyone on the ball enough to actively
update them as we were going it's just
too late by that point so but there has
been a pretty good response in terms of
ramping up production on masks and other
things and then 3m is like doubled the
production which is awesome and then
there's lots of DIY alternatives that
people are digging into I mean you can
make a pretty good mask using cotton and
vacuum cleaner bags and maybe a little
bit of a floral wire or twistiest you
know insert it in a way that allows you
to pinch the mask around your nose so
you can do a pretty good job there and
know a lot of plans out there for doing
that so that's the good side is that
we're you know responding well still not
as good as we could be on the flying
side but you know in terms of production
there's seem that kind of mobilization
story that we used to get from world war
ii where you know we switched over
production in a car plant two airplanes
in three months that kind of thing
seems to be working you know going from
a basket-case military in 1939
behind Portugal in terms of its
capabilities and then zooming it up to
where it was by 41 we're in that kind of
situation now that's good news let me
ask a couple questions about the good
news though you know we look back and
say what could we have done better one
of the things really hops out to me is
there was a very significant failure to
correctly flag integrate and push up the
chain in the intelligence that the
intelligence community was gathering in
the December and early January time
frame where things are coming out now
that is clear that analysts were
forecasting that this will had a fair
chance to become a global pandemic if we
had spent ten million dollars in
December and fifty million dollars in
January and ramping up testing we'd be
in a very different place than we are
today
any thoughts on how these intelligent
signals didn't get appropriately
prioritized and escalated and turned
into action yeah I think by late January
there were a lot of intelligence
briefings going out that said that this
would become a pandemic in fact if you
looked out on the net - there were
people talking about it I wrote my
January global Gorillaz report and
entitled pandemic it was about this
thing getting out of China and because
of the way that is the virus acted it
would it would zoom everywhere so there
were signals out there but the
assumption was that the planners the
bureaucracy the people who did this and
get paid for this would be able to pull
it off pull off the response pull off
the appropriate thing it's not like this
is stuff it is all made up on the fly
though you know like I said the planning
assumptions that were built into the
plants that we did have weren't
sufficient they were all geared to a
pandemic of the 80s and 90s you know it
people assume that they know that all
this stuff is all you know maybe use of
you know byproduct of being in the trump
era that all of this is made up on the
go but it's not I mean it's this is
stuff that has been thought through when
we paid billions for planning and
efforts in preparation just for this
moment then it all fell short yeah we'd
also didn't pull the trigger I mean I
guess that my point was these signals
were coming out
you know light signals in December and
stronger in January right and yet the
powers that be did not really seem to
understand the urgency until maybe the
very last week in February the first
week in January I mean that there's some
deep failure in intelligence coupled to
executive action in that ran it the way
oh yeah no definitely there was
definitely a longer delay in terms of
containment because there's I mean
there's four layers to you know
confronting the pandemic is the
mitigation you know basically social
distancing in school closures and stuff
you do mostly on the decentralized side
and then there's containment which is
travel restrictions and that's where the
presidency really could have played a
much better role and then the isolation
a case tracking that was all done
through bureaucracy you know you need a
lot of tests though and that needs
industries participation to do that and
then the final thing is quarantines I'm
more concerned now is about the big
negative is is just a scattershot
approach to containing it I mean we have
a couple big states taking extraordinary
measures too late Cuomo trying to you
know compensate for de Blasio's delay in
taking measures but most of the states
are doing almost nothing and this is
kind of a situation it's like um you
know we're headed towards based on most
estimates you know 50% reduction in GDP
and a 30% unemployment level within a
month at this rate you know with most of
the major economies of the you know
within the United States a you know shut
down and quarantined the timer has been
set you know the longer this persists
the the more likely that bad effect will
be kind of locked in will be actually in
a depression even if we get a hold of
the virus and all of this delay is just
lengthening at a time to return to
normal economic operation so it's better
trying to take all of the pain upfront
or as close to up front as you can by
taking measures early and we're not
doing that there's a lot of if not only
just States saying no it's also even
within states there's some states
of real problems enforcing quarantines
enforcing measures now people are out
and goofing off and doing whatever they
do and I mean I think the attitudes
towards those people will shift over the
next couple weeks from you know that's
just stupid or that's you know
inconsiderate or that kind of thing
towards wait a second those folks are
setting us up for a depression because
this couldn't lengthen this and the more
at length since the recovery effort the
more likely we're going to lose income
and not have a job coming out of this
and those people are actually stealing
from me let alone putting putting
relatives at risk or putting me at risk
they won't come back to that talk a
little bit about the cognitive
psychology of these people but before
that do you have any updates or any
sense of what's going on and say
California who blew the whistle first
and shut the whole state down for six
counties and then the whole state is
there any data coming out of California
yet to show that we're bending the
curves I mean if this is actually being
done it almost has to but I have seen
nothing on the data front yet I haven't
seen that yet in California somebody was
just sending me data from New York and
saying that three-day rolling average in
New York is starting to curve around in
the right direction you know the testing
blitz has helped them out a lot they've
been sucking up a lot of the country's
tests and they've taken it seriously at
least at the state level but there's you
know a lot of non-compliance at the New
York City level not sure that they're
actually capturing all of the
transmission that's occurring in that
space but yeah I think I think New York
is probably showing the the earliest
signs of a turnaround the Boston area
was you know early in its ability to you
know move from one of the four initial
epicenters to to kind of an also-ran in
number of cases and deaths but the
pressure from kind of the bleed out from
New York is pretty intense
just being next to that mega epicenter
is it's going to wear on Massachusetts
and and upper New England other
everywhere else it looks pretty much out
of control the one that worries me the
most right now is New Jersey
it's wow it's got a inverted
testing system it's like twenty haight
hundred positives for 300 all right 300
negatives in it's like wow I mean talk
about under testing virtually every
person they give the test who has it
that's scary yeah at this stage that's
crazy ought to be at least 90% positive
negative zat this point oh yeah most of
the states you know a lot of states are
in that you know 90% negative space but
Wow New Jersey I just something
seriously went wrong there and I've
surged you gone into a full lockdown yet
not that I've seen it's just a couple
days ago I saw some news saying that
they were fighting to keep the casinos
open so I don't think the news has
gotten to them yet well let's talk about
this I mean we've learned a lot and
we're I'm for sure processing lots of
things from this whole you know once in
a hundred year episode but the one to my
mind its most striking is what I would
say how highlighted it it has made the
issue of cognitive differences amongst
people even people you know similar
nominal intelligence there's some people
who immediately get it they understand
what an exponential is you know that the
current case loads two weeks ago didn't
mean jack shit because the low testing
rates and started taking very strong
actions and then there are other people
who are you know still you know going
out to restaurants or buy and take out
sandwiches or what-have-you and you'd
say by everything we know about them in
terms of their career and their
background their aptitude they should
have come to similar conclusions but
they didn't great any sense of of was
all about yeah I think we're really
seeing how network dynamics works in a
you know modern crisis I mean it's
really kind of giving us all a lesson in
it you know it's I'm still trying to get
my head around it I mean I was just
working on the whole idea of you know
what happens when you have you know
whole population network or
socio-economic network like ours in
siege mode and they kind of locks itself
in through these you know network
connections into this like I can't spend
money I can't go out even when you lift
the
restrictions how do you get that thing
moving again and that you have to
rethink everything you know about the
way we did economic bailouts in the past
you know the old bailout system is all
kind of interest group driven and it's a
usually some kind of power law
distribution where you know 1% get 40%
you know the top 20 get 80 to 90% of all
the money it has really little effect
and I'm moving the entire network and
after the financial crisis we saw that
that you know cause like a 10-year kind
of dig out that to get out of that kind
of you know under siege mentality and
this one's going to be much worse so I
was thinking about ways actually get
that whole network to shift
simultaneously and go positive and it
would you know that the stimulus program
would have to be universal or inclusive
everybody so kind of a consensus that we
all can come around and that would go
into a you know a positive towards our
cohesion and then more cohesion means
better coherence in terms of our
decision-making and then it has to be
significant relative to the the problem
that you know has to be big enough that
catches people's attention it has to
have some duration like if you were
getting like an emergency UVI you'd get
a you know $1,000 a month or the next
year or two years and you know that that
thing would be there and you could plan
against it and then take action in your
life that would allow you to utilize
that resource which then you know lost
people to dig out and then you know they
have some you know positive and Pro
building economic activity going on in
their life and there's lots of other
little ones I put in and put into my I
started a pandemic 2020 working space
where I just every day I have put more
stuff in and that was one of the things
I was working on this morning but this
this this group it's interesting because
we didn't have like the federal
government come down and say okay
everybody go into quarantine it was a
decentralized decision making process a
Merrill you mean think it's hard to even
think of the authority mechanism that
they would use to do that
and
unlike you know all these other
countries where everything came down
from on high what is driving the the
quarantine is that we have a network of
people who have decided based on you
know going through the evidence and
going through the information that that
we need to take drastic action they've
come to that consensus decision and and
they're pushing their states to take
action and that decision and and and the
amount of economic value that this group
generates puts us on a path towards
quarantine and you know putting the
economy on hold until the thing is
solved now you have what we've seen in
the you know Internet and the network is
that this free information flow allows a
lot of outliers to develop networks a
cluster set of people who are thinking
it you know differently and they can
self reinforce or you know they can
reinforce each other and they can often
stake out an alternative position and in
this case they've taken positions that
are contrary to that larger network now
here's the problem is that the this kind
of outlier position and at least when
when it comes to this pandemic
only exacerbates the economic damage
that would damage them because it delays
the time to when we get the quarantine
lifted it's really hard to lift the
quarantine when there's many states that
are still producing virus and you know
still a kind of shedding virus because
they're LexA days ago efforts we're kind
of this is the lowest common denominator
kind of problem where we have to get
everybody on board so we have to figure
out ways in which those clusters are
actually we can eat them down or get
them to join in and you know coming up
with you know methodologies of doing
that is pretty important flattening the
curve was was good that I just started
one this morning is going to buy time
for the test you know if this test rap
continues we'd be up two million semi
tests somewhere million tests a day a
lot of them 45-minute turnaround some of
whom trying to come up with instant
tests we're moving toward ubiquitous
testing you know that can help a lot but
it has to be done within the context of
an effort that they keeps the virus from
progressing to a level that we're
testing is in
effective because testing is tied to you
know contact tracing it's tied to
isolation it's tied to lots of other
things that it works best when the
number of people infected are at a
moderate level so anyway yeah it's just
thinking through the you know how how
this socio-economic system works as a as
a network no one I you know I looked
around and I talked to was talking to
Jordan about this it's like there's no
institution that addresses it so we have
the you know the Fed works on keeping
the financial system liquid and you know
knows how to do that knows how to keep
those banks you know lending and working
and and it keeps you know the market
buoyed enough and keeps us see keeps the
whole thing greased in the right way so
it doesn't seize up and then you have
the Congress who focuses on addressing
the needs of given interest groups and
they're really good at that kind of you
know giving them enough money that they
don't cleave off completely and then you
don't have this middle thing this new
work where that you can get this network
lock and where people just go under
siege or or the en masse kind of make a
decision that can't be reversed through
those other mechanisms or it takes a
long time to kind of unlock them from
that men the kind of the network health
the you know of our socio-economic socio
political system there's no one no one
really addressing that I mean we have a
little you know you can do with maybe a
little bit on Facebook in terms of mass
messaging and and and simple kind of
nudging and persuasion but you know
there's a there's a new model emerging
here just have to figure out all the
levers on it and also we're operating
and you know there's something you've
written a whole lot about and you know
I've been interested in it as well which
is the emergences of these highly
decentralized sense-making
networks and unfortunately those are
partially maladaptive to the kind of
situation we currently have well right
we're coherence and at least anecdotally
I would say pretty large and anecdotally
for people I've interacted with the not
taking it seriously lagging on
preparation etc seems strongly
correlated with membership or
association with
those particularly red Republican
FoxNews oriented outlier collective
sense making networks that seemed to
have not made sense the fact they made
anti sense and some of them still are
early Trump adopters are pretty much all
on the pandemic front yeah a few of the
good ones are like Bannon and Qurna
bitch and guys like that yeah and
frankly it was Tucker Carlson who I
think finally sat that idiot trump down
and smacked him across the face for two
hours and made him pay attention but
unfortunately when you look at the
topology of the the red collective sense
making networks the main repeater is
Trump you know things circularly they
can circulate up through various layers
and they get up the Trump then he
broadcasts and then they go back out and
become modified and evolved but that
motherfucker never got it he still
hasn't gotten it and if he were a strong
decisive leader he could Co here the red
collective intelligence networks you
know back on board much more rapidly so
it seems to me a grotesque failure of
top-level leadership by the president
yeah I think I read it a little bit
differently I mean not that it's you
know I think he's making a lot of the
wrong decisions but also I think it's
more like okay for instance last night
he was talking about ending the crisis
yeah but that yeah the way I read it is
that he's actually bad as a negotiation
or you know as part of his negotiation
with with the Democrats for his
bailout package because if you won't let
me solve this crisis using my bailout
package then let's just to solve the
crisis and it's it's a crazy position
it's right out of his negotiation kind
of handbook you know it's a the art of
the deal it's you know take a crazy
position and convinced me to move off of
it and then and when I do you're happy
with what I give you and he's done that
a couple of times during this crisis
this is one of them oh yeah understand
that this is wartime this is not some
sleazy real-estate deal Atlantic City
we're dealing with lives of millions of
people here and we can't be playing the
egocentric horseshit fucking games you
know I never liked Trump I've always
despised him as a human being but this
crisis has brought out him at his
absolute worse I mean you know that
unbelievably evil little snide remark
about Romney what is wrong with that man
right hopefully this will be a huge
lesson to the American people
character fucking matters do not vote
for a person of known rotten character
no matter what you how much you agree
with them on the issues yeah well his
approval for and on the crisis is in the
50s now so it's exactly having the
opposite effect
it's a it's an interesting thing I mean
I think you mentioned Carlson I still
think that guy he has a better year for
the network he it it's interesting if
you're a politician at the national
level now you have to really be
effective either on the left or the
right you you have to have your ear open
to the network and listen to those
outlier positions and often a lot of the
truth of things that you should be doing
or out there and the edges and Carlson
tends to pick that kind of truth
messaging up and I think he's really
going to be a pretty strong candidate
for the Republicans in in four years how
about this year man it's it's a I think
it's too late to turn that but in four
years I think he's gonna run the
actuarial attributes of coronavirus may
open up that door yeah yeah there's
still time and that for Korona to
actually make the decisive vote in the
presidential campaign
I didn't Biden has been totally absent
he's like I mean I'm watching even
Delaware and Delaware is one of the
states on the bad boy list in terms of
response so um I don't know I mean you
know I mean Biden has nothing other than
saying that he's electable a platitude
he's the king of all platitudes and you
know he's not Trump he's not clinically
insane though he might be demented what
a fuckin country we have that those are
our two choices something fundamentally
wrong with our whole system let's go
back briefly here though before we wrap
up to this economic response
let's see I've been writing about a lot
on Twitter and on Facebook and it
strikes me that you're exactly right it
can't be a top-down it can't be a
burrito 80% 20% of people get 80% of the
schwag and most of it wasted this has
got to be bottoms up it's got to be a
mini ubi universal basic income and I've
also been saying I look at your reaction
of this that we can't be screwing around
with anything that requires any systems
development any complexity because
frankly or emotionally and
intellectually overloaded by the crisis
and what I've been proposing is that you
put it out to a three day bid to the
biggest credit card companies and say
all right people here's the drill it's
all going to be done with plastic debit
cards sent out monthly start by setting
- everybody's IRS filing address for
those that don't have an IRS filing
address they can register at any bank
and they'll tap them into a real simple
system for welfare and homeless welfare
departments could literally hand these
cards out on the street take a biometric
picture and submit that to a database
and then here's the part that I like of
my own idea of my own ideas are always
good so what the hell fuck and that's
that the cards have a 45-day time to
live you haven't spent your 45 days on
on your April card
it disappears goes back into the into
the pool to be redistributed so that we
aren't subject to you know the famous
paradox of thrift where well thrift in
some ways is a good thing in a situation
like this if everybody saves we all die
or the economy dies so the beauty of
specific cards and a new card sent out
monthly yes it raises the cost a little
bit but the time to live on the money on
each card provides a huge force to get
people to actually get that damn thing
into the economy I mean there's a lot of
a lot of little private currencies had
that same kind of thing it was kind of
like a negative interest rate de Mirage
as we call it ya de Mirage exactly and
you know it kind of gets you to spend
them this is more brutal though this is
a clip 45 where it goes back into the
common pool and put it right on the card
this money expires on say the April
first card expires on May 15 put alright
on the card and I think you know that
way we get rid of
all needs for fancy new systems we can
deal with everybody from the homeless to
you know the regular homeowner we can
run it as many months as we need to it
does have a little bit higher operations
cost but it seems to me at this point a
little bit higher operations costs is
way superior to taking you know systems
development risks fancy processing risks
that a lot of people aren't going to be
able to hop through quickly because
they're not supposed to leave the house
etc so I think the big thing here too is
that if you really look at this like a
emergency ubi over two years in you know
conjunction with this crisis and what it
can do I mean it cost the price tag
quite a little over four trillion
dollars it's a lot but you know
borrowing at 30% or borrowing 30 years
at less than 1% is it's pretty
attractive in in terms of financing it
but I think unlike those all of these
bail out bills and these multi there's
the one that the Democrats are proposing
you're two and a half trillion so you're
you're almost there unlike those this
would have a very strong ROI and then
any kind of like real stimulus a real
kind of paddles to the to the chest of
the economy or socio economy with a
stopped heart is you could actually show
if you measure it you know with a lot of
focus you know that this thing is
actually generating two three four five
times returns over the over a 30-year
period I mean because if you can bounce
us out of this this crisis early return
us to where we were maybe zoom us a
little rocket fuel on the economy and
getting us up to say a 10% rate next
year that is is just gold I mean you
look at any kind of study right now an
ubi is always that that's that the
effects last you don't bounce back from
it when it's gone at last it builds
infrastructure it builds capital
actually because you know in our current
world we have actually an excess of
capital in some sense in financial
capital you know why is all this money
sitting in banks not being lent out but
we had demand push that capital becomes
mobilized we actually create things it's
an investment look at 30 30 year bond at
less than 1% shows that this vast pool
of capital at the global level is
looking is screaming at the United
States say just
invest it because you know there's got
to be a way to do that this is going to
you know yield a positive return you
know inside the United but what better
way to invest it and even though it's
wasted it you invest in Americans and
Americans let them invest that that
money you know you know three hundred
and twenty actually probably two hundred
fifty million adults all making
decisions I where to spend it will yield
much better results in a lot of the
government bureaucrats would if they
were focusing in on unbaling money
yeah the Democrats errors they want to
give it to the state-level bureaucrats
the Republican errors they want to give
it to big corporations most of whom it's
inappropriate for and the real answer is
to give it to the fucking people right
that's the answer you know all the
people listen to the show call your
Congressman call your senator tell them
that eighty percent at least of this
money needs to be in the form of
universal basic income grants going out
to the people
monthly let me talk briefly about the
corporate side you know Airlines that's
ridiculous we shouldn't be giving any
money to the airline companies because
we airline companies have come and gone
forever the key thing about airlines are
the airplanes the pilots the mechanic
the stewardess the gates etc and those
things get recombined into new economic
entities the shareholders and the
bondholders take it up the poop chute oh
well that's life the actual elements
that you need to run an airline or
physical intangible and survive any
failure the only the only companies we
should be investing in are ones with
very deep intellectual property creation
stacks like Boeing like Intel like the
automobile companies and I'm sure Harma
suitable although they're not gonna have
a problem probably but we should that we
should not be trucking is another
example yeah trucking sneaking it up
taking it on the chin oh well
trucking companies also come and go at a
very high rate and trucks will be
recombined and with drivers under new
corporate umbrellas it will be debt-free
because the old ones were wiped out the
trucks were bought for twenty cents on
the dollar so ridiculous for the feds to
try to pump prop up trucking companies
but trucking companies
a huge lobby as do airlines and so again
let's tell our elected officials really
think smart about what industries we
must have that we lose the capability if
we let them go away and they're
basically only the deep IP stack
companies you know like the Boeing isn't
like the Intel's and let's not take the
asset recombination companies and prop
them up because frankly we get that a
refactoring for free and frankly those
industries will be better off once
they're refracted away and free from
debt correct I agree it's it gets more
interesting when you look at
universities yeah well yeah do you keep
do you you know do you help them make
the transition to doing more of what
they do online and a lot of that
physical plant and a lot of that
personnel kind of overhead becomes
unneeded do you help them restructure I
think we probably have to but whether
they should be the ones to restructure
or not I'm not so sure tell you the
truth you know they're if they
restructure they're gonna do it a
ponderous self-serving way so I think
I'm gonna reserve judgment on whether
they should be provided a massive
bailout to transition or competitors
ought to be allowed to rise up and take
their market share right or making it
easier to get high-quality degrees
online because everyone's really just
after the certificate ring well that's
unfortunate in which case they shouldn't
waste their time you know you know a
guild type certifications is what my
view the game B world will be about
where there'll be guilds for every
occupation and it'll be their job to
certify people within their guild and
pay scales will typically be within
bands around Gil sort guild
certification levels you're a Python
level four that means you're between 70
and 100 and 105 dollars an hour and your
guild stands behind your certification
and if they're not doing a good job
certifying the guild rate people will
stop paying it so they'll have a strong
incentive you know self-administer
competency tests and also for members of
the guild part of their income will go
back to the guild in terms of which will
provide training for them to ramp their
skills up I see that as a much better
model than these unbelievably ponderous
higher education factories that we have
today anyway there will be some very
interesting changes on the other side of
this John I appreciate your time here
today for this first kickoff special
coronavirus podcast and continue to look
forward to reading your very good work
on global guerillas on patreon great
thanks Jim yeah I'm writing everyday now
so it's a lot of stuff it's constantly
evolving it's a lot of fun take care and
thanks for having me on production
services and audio editing by Jared
Jane's consulting music by Tom Muller at
modern space music.com
[Music]